Guide to the Anaconda Copper Mining Company records 1876-1974
Montana Historical Society
Anaconda Copper Mining Company records
1876-1974
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 169
Anaconda Copper Mining Company
800 linear feet of shelf space
This collection consists of records (1876-1974) of the Anaconda Copper Mining Company and contains correspondence, court papers, financial and production records, legal documents, organizational records, subject files, and other materials for the Anaconda Copper Mining Company and many of its predecessor and subsidiary companies and departments. Among the major subgroups are General Office; Big Blackfoot Milling Company; Bitter Root Development Company; Boston and Montana Consolidated Copper and Silver Mining Company; Colorado Smelting and Mining Company; Diamond Coal and Coke Company; Parrot Silver and Copper Company; Reduction Department (Anaconda); Silver Bow Club; Trenton Mining and Development Company; Tuttle Manufacturing and Supply Company; and Washoe Copper Company. In addition, there are more than 100 smaller subgroups.
Historical Note:
In 1876 Walker Brothers, a Salt Lake City, Utah, mining and banking firm, hired Marcus Daly to investigate silver mining properties in Butte, Montana. The Walkers and Daly purchased the Alice Mine and incorporated as the Alice Gold and Silver Mining Company. Daly served as general superintendent until he sold his interest in the company in 1880.
That same year he bought the Anaconda Mine, located by Michael Hickey in October 1875. Hickey, unable to keep up annual assessment work on the mine, had sold half interest in it to Charles Larabie, a banker. Larabie brought in Daly as a third partner to sink a shaft. Daly got an option from his partners to purchase the property for $30,000 and tried to interest the Walker Brothers in investing in it. When they declined, Daly went to San Francisco and secured the backing of James Haggin, George H. Hearst, and Lloyd Tevis. The four men operated the mine under a partnership arrangement as a silver property. The small quantities of copper which the mine produced were shipped to Swansea, Wales, for processing. In late 1882 a rich copper vein was struck.
As copper became the main product of the mine, Daly decided to build his own smelter instead of continuing the expensive procedure of shipping ore to Wales. He located a suitable site on Warm Springs Greek, twenty six miles west of Butte. He officially platted the new town of Anaconda on October 27, 1883, and began the construction of what became known as the Upper Works. Transportation of the Butte ores to the new smelter was provided by the narrow-gauge Montana Railway. This railroad, under the name Montana Union Railway, was later operated jointly by the Union Pacific and Northern Pacific companies. The original 500-ton capacity mill, completed in 1884, quickly became inadequate and, within two years, was expanded to 1000 tons. During the early years, only the initial stages of treatment were done at the Anaconda Reduction Works, with the concentrated ore still being shipped to Wales for refining. To eliminate this necessity, Daly built an experimental electrolytic refinery, completed in 1888. He also built a second reduction plant, known as the Lower Works, a mile east of the Upper Works. Fire destroyed this plant shortly after its completion. Daly quickly rebuilt on an even larger scale.
While Daly was developing the Anaconda Reduction Works, he was also expanding the basis of his mining operations. Until 1891 the Haggin-Hearst-Tegin-Daly syndicate had operated its Montana properties as a partnership under the name Anaconda Gold and Silver Mining Company. In January 1891 when it incorporated as the Anaconda Mining Company, the company owned four groups of mines: the Anaconda Group, the Mountain Consolidated Group, the Union Consolidated Group, and the Anglo-Saxon Group. Daly, Hearst, and Tegin owned only the minimum shares required by law. Haggin held the remainder in trust. The Anaconda Mining Company reinvested all profits in building its facilities instead of giving dividends.
From 1891 to 1895 the Anaconda Mining Company began the process of consolidating its control over its services and sources of raw materials. Angered by the Montana Union Railway's high charges and inefficient service, Daly built his own railroad, the Butte, Anaconda, and Pacific, to connect the smelter with the mines. The Big Blackfoot Milling Company and the Bitter Root Development Company were created as allied companies to provide Anaconda with needed timber. The Castner Coal and Coke Company, with Daly as a minor stockholder, provided the company with coal. The Tuttle Manufacturing and Supply Company was formed to meet the smelter's foundry and hardware needs. When a larger smelter was needed to meet increased treatment requirements at Anaconda, the Washoe Copper Company was created to build the New Reduction Works, which was then operated by Anaconda under a lease arrangement.
In 1895 the company was again reorganized, this time as the Anaconda Copper Mining Company, with a capitalization of $30,000,000. Haggin's trust-held properties were transferred to the new company and, over the next year, several of the allied companies were brought in as subsidiaries.
In 1899 H.H. Rogers and A.C. Burrage, officers of the Standard Oil Company and stockholders in the Anaconda Copper Mining Company, urged the union of all Butte mining operations under one holding company. In April 1899 the Amalgamated Copper Company was formed to acquire the stock of the Anaconda Copper Mining Company and its subsidiary companies including the Big Blackfoot Milling Company, the Bitter Root Development Company, the Diamond Coal and Coke Company, the Tuttle Manufacturing and Supply Company, and the Washoe Copper Company. In addition, the Amalgamated acquired several other previously unallied Butte mining companies including the Boston and Montana Consolidated Copper and Silver Mining Company and the Parrot Silver and Copper Company. The Amalgamated Copper Company was simply a holding company and was not involved in management of the various companies, which continued to operate independently. The most important of the companies brought under the Amalgamated umbrella was the Boston and Montana. It owned several important mining claims in Butte (including the Mountain View and East Colusa) and a smelter in Great Falls. This smelter, built in 1892, duplicated many of the facilities in Anaconda, handling all levels of ore processing from concentration to refining.
In 1910 the Anaconda Copper Mining Company took over most of the other companies in the Amalgamated Copper Company, all Amalgamated subsidiaries becoming departments within Anaconda. One of the most important results of this reorganization was that it allowed the two major reduction works at Anaconda and Great Falls to coordinate their operations. Anaconda continued to handle the early stages of concentrating and smelting, while Great Falls gradually phased out these operations and specialized in refining. All stages prior to refining were finally eliminated from Great Falls in 1919. At the same time, Great Falls increased its refining capacity by the addition of an electrolytic zinc plant. In 1915 the Amalgamated Copper Company ended its corporate existence.
During the period that Anaconda Copper Mining Company was consolidating its Montana operations, it was also expanding towards its goal of controlling copper "from mine to consumer." In 1913 the company acquired the International Smelting and Refining Company, which owned smelters at Tooele, Utah, and Miami, Arizona, as well as the Raritan Copper Works in New Jersey. In 1922 Anaconda bought the American Brass Company in Waterbury, Connecticut, one of the major producers of finished copper products. Also in the early 192Os, Anaconda invested in Chile, acquiring the Chuquicamata copper mine from the Guggenheim family, as well as the smaller, but important, Potrerillos mine. It acquired from the heirs of Georg von Giesche a large zinc treatment plant at Katowice, Poland. In 1928 W.A. Clark's heirs sold his Montana companies to Anaconda. In 1955, in recognition of the wide range of corporate operations, the company name was changed to The Anaconda Company.
The company prospered during World War II and the years following. Several ambitious projects, including the Greater Butte Project to expand underground operations and the Berkeley Pit to commence surface mining, were undertaken. In 1971, however, Chile nationalized the Chuquicamata and other American-owned mines. This, along with low copper prices brought about a financial crisis. Forced to meet financial deadlines in New York, the company sold its entire lumber operation, including thousands of square miles of Montana timber land and the Bonner mill, to Champion International. This liquidation, however, did not solve the company's financial problems, and in 1979 the company was purchased by the Atlantic-Richfield Company (ARCO). Over the next few years, ARCO shut down its entire Montana operation, including the Berkeley Pit in Butte, the Anaconda Smelter, and the Great Falls Refinery.
The Anaconda Copper Mining Company Records consist of correspondence, court papers, financial and production records, legal documents, organizational records, subject files, and other materials for the company and many of its predecessor and subsidiary companies and departments. Among the major subgroups into which the collection is arranged are the General Office, the Big Blackfoot Milling Company, the Bitter Root Development Company, the Boston and Montana Consolidated Copper and Silver Mining Company, the Butte and Boston Consolidated Mining Company, the Colorado Smelting and Mining Company, the Diamond Coal and Coke Company, the Parrot Silver and Copper Company, the Reduction Department (Anaconda), the Trenton Mining and Development Company, the Tuttle Manufacturing and Supply Company, and the Washoe Copper Company. In addition, there are more than one hundred smaller subgroups (see Table of Contents). Unconnected with the primary mining, smelting and timber operations of the Company were several affiliated companies in the hotel and related fields; oil and gas development; water and townsite companies; and newspaper publishing. Subgroups for these include the Silver Bow Club, the Florence Hotel and the Montana Hotel; the West Dome Oil Company; the Anaconda Townsite Company and the Hamilton Water Company; and the Post Publishing Company and the Montana Free Press.
Among the more significant operations documented in this collection are the General Office, both in Butte and in Anaconda; the various subsidiary operations, both before and after their absorption into Anaconda; and the two large treatment plants, the Anaconda Smelter and the Great Falls Refinery. Among the subjects documented are the technical and economic details of the two smelters; the company's large lumber operations in the Missoula area; the company's coal mines; relations with employees; and treatment and recovery of tailings, including the related issue of air and water pollution. There is less documentation for the core mining operations in Butte.
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in Archives Map Case, Manuscript Volumes, and oversize boxes. See Location of Collection information above and inventory below for more information.
Some of the General Office financial ledgers have been microfilmed.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Maps, printed material, photographs, and artifacts transferred to the MHS Library, Photo Archives, and Museum respectively. See inventory below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Anaconda Copper Mining Company
Albright (Mont.); Basin (Mont.); Bearcreek (Mont.); Belt (Mont.); Black Eagle Dam (Mont.); Black Eagle (Mont.); Anaconda (Mont.); Arizona; Armington (Mont.); Bonanza Mines (Darwin, Calif.); Bonita (Mont.); Bonner (Mont.); Butte (Mont.); Carbon (Mont.); Carbonado (Mont.); Carroll (Deer Lodge County, Mont.); Cascade County (Mont.). Health Dept.; Cascade County (Mont.); Chile; Chuquicamata Mine (Chile); Cokedale (Mont.); Columbia Falls (Mont.); Darby (Mont.); Darwin Mines (Darwin, Calif.); East Helena (Mont.); Elliston (Mont.); Fort Benton (Mont.); Fort Peck Dam (Mont.); Giant Springs (Mont.); Gold Butte (Mont.); Great Falls (Mont.); Hamilton (Mont.); Hope (Idaho); Houghton (Mich.); Idaho; Mexico; Michigan; Missoula (Mont.); Missouri Headwaters State Park (Mont.); Missouri River--Power utilization; Missouri River--Barrages; Neihart (Mont.); Norway.; Poland.; Rainbow Dam (Mont.); Rocker (Mont.); Snohomish Mine (Wash.); St. Regis (Mont.); Storrs (Mont.); Thompson Falls (Mont.); Utah; Victoria Mines (Elko, Nev.); Washington (State); Wyoming
Air--Pollution--Montana; Assaying; Blacksmiths--Montana; Boardinghouses--Montana; Bowling--Montana; Brickmaking--Montana; Charities--Montana; Coal mines and mining; Coal trade--Montana; Coke industry--Montana; Company stores--Montana; Arsenic; Clay mines and mining--Montana; Copper mines and mining--Montana--Butte; Dams --Montana; Electric power--Montana; Electric utilities--Montana; Fertilizer; Fire prevention--Montana; Flumes--Montana; Foundries--Montana--Anaconda; Gold mines and mining--Montana; Grazing leases--Montana; Hardware stores--Montana; Hospitals--Montana; Hotels--Montana; Industrial safety--Montana; Insurance; Iron mines and mining--Montana; Labor disputes--Montana; Laboratories--Montana; Land companies--Montana; Lead mines and mining--Montana; Lime industry--Montana; Lumber trade--Idaho; Lumber trade--Montana; Manganese mines and mining--Montana; Meat industry and trade--Montana; Metallurgy; Meteorology--Montana--Great Falls; Mine safety--Montana; Mineralogy; Mines and mineral resources--Arizona; Mines and mineral resources--California; Mines and mineral resources--Chile; Mines and mineral resources--Idaho; Mines and mineral resources--Mexico; Mines and mineral resources--Michigan; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Carbon County; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Cascade County; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Silver Bow County; Mines and mineral resources--Utah; Mines and mineral resources--Wyoming; Mining engineering--Montana; Newspapers--Montana; Natural gas--Montana; Ore-dressing--Montana; Ores--Sampling and estimation; Ores--Transportation; Paint industry and trade--Montana; Patents; Pensions--Montana; Petroleum industry and trade--Montana; Phosphate mines and mining--Montana; Physicians--Montana; Pollution--Montana; Quarries and quarrying--Montana; Railroads--Montana; Real estate business--Montana; Recreation--Montana; Retail trade--Montana; Scrap metals--Montana; Silver mines and mining--Montana; Smelting--Montana--Anaconda; Smelting--Montana--East Helena; Smelting--Montana--Great Falls; Reduction works--Montana--Anaconda; Reduction works--Montana--Great Falls; Clubs --Montana--Butte; Clubs --Montana--Great Falls; Strikes and lockouts--Copper mining--Montana; Sugar beet industry--Montana; Tailings (Metallurgy)--Montana; Taxation--Montana; Telephone--Montana; Townsites--Montana; Labor unions--Montana; Labor unions--Machinists--Montana; Labor unions--Miners--Montana; Labor unions--Smelter workers--Montana; Tramps--Montana; Vocational education--Montana; Wages --Montana; Water--Pollution--Montana; Water-power--Montana--Great Falls; Water-supply--Montana; Municipal water supply--Montana; Welfare work in industry--Montana; Workers' compensation--Montana--Law and legislation; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945--Civil defense--Montana; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Montana; Zinc mines and mining--Montana
Idaho; Montana; Washington (State)
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Office
  - Incoming Correspondence [Anaconda Mining Company]
    - Anaconda Fluming Company, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: Marcus Daly, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: Michael Donahoe, 1889-1899 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: W. Flanagan, 1892-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: J.B. Haggin, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: J.F. Hayward, 1891-1892 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: H. Eck Moller, 1894-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: H.O. O'Connor, 1893 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: Victor Ray, 1892-1893 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: F.E. Sargeant, 1890-1894 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Anaconda Mining Company: B-W, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - A, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Baltimore Copper Smelting and Rolling Company, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Bitter Root Development Company, 1891-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - J.R. Boarman, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Butte City Sampling Works; Butte Sampling Works, 1893-1894 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - B, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - Castner Coal and Coke Company, 1894-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - J.B. Church (re Golden Pressed and Fire Brick Company), 1890-1894 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
    - C, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - M.J. Dignan, 1892-1893 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - G.W. Douglass and Company, 1893-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - D, 1891-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Electric Railway, Light and Power Company, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - Evens and Howard's Fire Brick, Clay Retort, and Sewer Pipe Works, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - E, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - Fraser and Chalmers, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - F-G, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 8-9)
    - William Harrison (re Baxendale granite quarry), 1893-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - George H. Hull and Company, 1891-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - H, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - I-K, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Lewisohn Brothers, 1894 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - L, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - James McFarlane, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
    - Montana Union Railway Company, 1889-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
    - M, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
    - Northern Pacific Railroad Company, 1890-1894 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
    - N-P, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 20-22)
    - W.R. Richards and Company, 1890-1891 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
    - Rocky Mountain Bell Telephone Company, 1892-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
    - R, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
    - St. Paul and Tacoma Lumber Company, 1890-1893 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Silver Bow Sampling Works, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Standard Fire Brick Company, 1890-1894 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - S, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - Tuttle Manufacturing and Supply Company, 1891-1895 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - T, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Union Fire Brick Company, 1890-1892 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
    - Union Pacific Railway Company, 1890-1894 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
    - U-V, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
    - Wilson and Gillie, Civil Engineers, 1892-1894 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - R.D. Wood and Company, 1892-1893 (Box-folder 3 / 11)
    - W-Z, 1890-1895 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Incoming Correspondence [Anaconda Copper Mining Company]
    - American Express Company, 1895-1899 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Charles Boylan, 1895-1898 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Marcus Daly, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 3 / 15-16)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Chester B. Davis, 1898 (Box-folder 3 / 17)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: J.S. Dougherty, 1896-1898 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: J.B. Haggin, 1895-1898 (Box-folder 3 / 19-20)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: H.R. Ismon, 1899 (Box-folder 3 / 21)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: A.H. Melin, 1898 (Box-folder 3 / 22)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: H. Eck Moller, 1895-1899 (Box-folder 4 / 1-5)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: F.E. Sargeant, 1896 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: E.C. Sickles, 1899-1900 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: W.T. Tyler, 1897 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Coal Department, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 4 / 9-10)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Electric Light and Railway Department, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 4 / 11)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Foundry Department, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: General Offices, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Hardware Department, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Legal Department, 1899 (Box-folder 5 / 2)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Lumber Department (Anaconda), 1896-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 3)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Lumber Department (Butte), 1897-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Lumber Department (Carbon, Columbia Falls), 1897-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Lumber Department (Hamilton), 1896-1899 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Mercantile Department (Anaconda, Belt), 1896-1899 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Mercantile Department (Hamilton), 1896-1899 (Box-folder 5 / 8)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Mine Office, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 9)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Mountain Consolidated Mine Office, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 5 / 10)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: New York offices, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 11)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Purchasing Department, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 12)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: Superintendent's Office, 1900 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company: miscellaneous offices, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 14)
    - Anaconda Fluming Company, 1895-1898 (Box-folder 5 / 15)
    - Astoria and Columbia River Railroad Company; The Astoria Company, 1898-1900 (Box-folder 5 / 16)
    - A, 1895-1899 (Box-folder 5 / 17)
    - Baltimore Copper Smelting and Rolling Company, 1895 (Box-folder 5 / 18)
    - Baltimore Copper Smelting and Rolling Company, 1896-1900 (Box-folder 6 / 1-3)
    - Belt Mercantile Company, 1895 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Big Blackfoot Lumber Company; Big Blackfoot Milling Company, 1898-1900 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Bitter Root Development Company, 1895-1896 (Box-folder 6 / 6-7)
    - Bitter Root Stock Farm, 1895-1898 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - Boston and Montana Consolidated Copper and Silver Mining Company, 1899-1900 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
    - Henry Burrell, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
    - Butte, Anaconda, and Pacific Railway Company, 1895-1899 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
    - B, 1895-1899 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
    - Carbon Coal Company, 1898-1900 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
    - Castner Coal and Coke Company, 1895-1896 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
    - Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad Company, 1895-1898 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
    - Chicago, Milwaukee and St. Paul Railway Company, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 7 / 1)
    - W. Brodrick Cloete (re investment in Explorations), 1898 (Box-folder 7 / 2)
    - Colorado Fuel and Iron Company, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 7 / 3)
    - Colorado Smelting and Mining Company, 1898-1899 (Box-folder 7 / 4)
    - C, 1895-1900 (Box-folder 7 / 5)
    - Daly and Company, 1897 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
    - Daly, Donahoe and Moyer, Bankers, 1899 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
    - Margaret P. Daly; Mary Augusta Daly, 1896 (Box-folder 7 / 8)
    - Daly Mining Company, 1895 (Box-folder 7 / 9)
    - Diamond Coal and Coke Company, 1897-1900 (Box-folder 7 / 10-11)